JUAN C. CONTRERAS

icontrmo@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/juancontrmo/

Certified professional Developer (Oracle Forms - Oracle Cloud - PLSQL - SQL) and Database administrator, in addition to Oracle Data Integrator (ODI) support and development experience, able to help customers to solve issues related to ELT mappings, performance, bug documentation, patching, testing, and ELT development.

Skilled problem identifier and troubleshooter in a range of IT environments with certified knowledge of Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI): Bilingual English-Spanish, US citizen with verified employment history, see www.hireright.com.

Objective

Looking for challenging Database Developer positions according to my knowledge and experience (SQL, Data Modeling, PL/SQL, ELT, Database Administration, Bash Shell, Oracle Cloud).

Summary of Skills

Oracle DBA, Oracle Forms Warehouse Oracle APEX, Jenkins

Education

<u>Universidad Antonio Nariño</u> – BS – Systems Engineering Bogota, D.C 1998

Certifications

- Oracle PL/SQL Certified Associate
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure Foundations
- Oracle Database Administrator
- Oracle Forms Developer

Technical videos:

YouTube channel "JC Contreras - Just a curious Tech Guy" Media channel with videos for Database Developers

Video #1: Data Integration example between Oracle and SQL Server Video #2: Connecting Oracle SQLDeveloper to OCI & AWS (Part I) Video #3: Connecting Oracle SQLDeveloper to OCI & AWS (Part II)

Video #4: PL/SQL for DBAs

Languages:

- English Advance Proficiency
- Spanish Native

Resume Spanish translation: https://jcontrmo.github.io/HojaVida/

Recent Training

- Oracle Database 12c: Backup and Recovery
- Learning Jenkins
- What Is Scrum?
- Learning Oracle Database 19c
- Learning Python
- Test Automation Foundations
- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (SAA-C01): 1 Cloud Services Overview
- Learning Linux Command Line
- Troubleshooting Common PC Issues for Users
- Learning PC Maintenance and Performance
- Microsoft SQL Server 2019 Essential Training
- Oracle Database 12c: Security
- Customer Service: Managing Customer Expectations
- Customer Service: Problem Solving and Troubleshooting
- CompTIA Network+ (N10-007) Cert Prep: 1 Understanding Networks
- Learning Cloud Computing: Networking
- New Manager Foundations

Professional Experience

<u>Self-Employed</u> – Research Engineer Orlando USA, FL Jul 15, 2020 – Present

- Research Technical integration issues as part of Database administration, Data integration, Database Development
- Review training for Oracle Data Integrator 12c Certified Implementation Specialist, test cases and documentation.
- Prepare Training for Students willing to get SQL advance knowledge
- Develop test case scenarios as part of deep research on Windows and Linux environments
- Install Oracle Databases, SQL Server databases latest versions on cloud and on-premise environments
- Create useful PLSQL, Bash Shell scripts to facilitate Database Administration and Development
- Document best practices for PLSQL coding
- Research automation techniques as part of Agile software development process

<u>ORACLE</u> – Senior Technical Support Engineer Orlando USA, FL Oct 21,2015 – Jul 15,2020

- Creation of ODI Source-target mapping among different technologies, reverse engineering, models generation, create package steps of different types, modified and developed knowledge modules, using mapping components and expressions, use variables in packages and several development techniques as part of internal training and issue reproduction to solve service requests.
- Troubleshooting simple to complex Oracle data integrator issues related to Data Warehouse for top account customers under SLAs predefined
- ODI upgrades from 11g to 12c versions for internal testing
- Provided recommendations related to ODI best practices for Data Warehouse.

- Configuration and design of virtual environments (database, OS, ODI agents) on Linux and Windows platforms to reproduce and solve ODI technical issues in Oracle Cloud environment.
- ODI Topology Configuration to handle data integration connectivity with several source & target technologies
- Tuning of ODI developments, Memory, IO checking to provide best practices to improve ODI performance in Oracle Cloud and on-premise environments
- Documentation of solved issues to be published on my Oracle Support site
- Code review (PLSQL, Bash shell) to troubleshoot ODI issues
- Worked with internal ticketing system (MOS) to facilitate customers' communication, documentation and escalation of service requests

INDRA – Database Administrator July 9,2012 – Jan 31,2014

Bogota, D.C.

- Installed, configured, and managed Oracle 10g, 11g on windows and Linux platform.
- Interacted with the Technical Design team and contributed in impact analysis and creation of the technical specifications.
- Manage Database administration assignments in SQL Server environments
- Worked on Oracle databases and MSSQL, this included backup, restoration, and quality control
 applications.
- Developed windows scripts, shell scripts, PL/SQL programming for automation of database administration tasks
- Detailed review of Oracle Forms and PL/SQL code on customers to troubleshoot performance issues as part of the customer's software design.
- Developed and created a definition of backup strategies for RMAN and EXPDP.
- Created database structures for developer and client needs on QA and production environments.
- Applied security patches on Oracle databases.
- Involved in session management and monitoring the critical wait events, blocking sessions in the databases (Oracle and MSSQL).
- Worked on Migration of Oracle 11g Databases from Windows to Linux on Production environment

<u>EUD</u> – IT Certification Trainer July 2011 – July 2012

Bogota, D.C.

- Training IT students in Database Administration, PL/SQL and Oracle Forms programming by using official Oracle documentation in order to help them to achieve Oracle Certifications.
- Installed databases and OS in classroom environments
- Provided recommendations to real issues happening on students' jobs related to PLSQL coding and Oracle Forms design according to best practices

SYNAPSIS (TIVIT) - Oracle Database Administrator Bogota, D.C May 5, 2010 - Dec 31, 2011

- Managed Oracle RMAN backups and tuning oracle sentences.
- Provided support for Oracle Data Guard administration
- Oracle database and MSSQL backups and recovery.
- Added more new features to existing analysis software tools.
- Created structural changes to the Oracle databases using DDL statements.
- Worked on Oracle configuration, third party backup software and backup testing.
- Supported DBA Junior SQL Server 2008 on replication scenario with log shipping.

- Made corrections of inefficient high load SQL statements, suboptimal use of Oracle database, undersized memory structures, concurrency issues, database configuration, and locking issues.
- Created Bash Shell scripts to invoke SQL Scripts and scheduled them using OS crontab
- Developed Complex PL/SQL Code, Stored Procedures, Functions, Packages and Triggers which uses collections as part of temporary developments assignments
- Applied analysis, data collection techniques, database normalization, entity relation modeling in SDLC from analysis, design, development, testing, implementation, and maintenance
- Reports generation based on multiple tables and subqueries by using ANSI SQL and T-SQL
- Involved in data loading using SQL Loader to load data from flat files
- Worked closely with clients to clarify development specifications

<u>Telefónica (Movistar)</u> – IT Database Professional – Bogotá, DC Nov 3, 2009 – Apr 1, 2010

- Utilize Oracle diagnostic tools like Explain Plan, SQL Trace, TKPROF and AWR to analyze timing and execution for database tuning
- Created and modified existing Unix scripts for Oracle 10g
- Managed Standard Audit trail, audit parameters
- Used triggers to record additional customized Audit information
- Worked with the development team for database object creation, query tuning and regular database related issues.
- Oracle database installation, patch installation, configuration, and maintenance.
- Tune the SQL queries by creating proper index, using hints, and changing database parameters
- Involved in development of application functions, triggers, PL/SQL and packages
- 24 x 7 database on call support according to shift rotation schedule

ORATECH LTDA

Aug 19, 2008 - Jul 22, 2009 Position: Infrastructure Consultant

- Managed the Oracle database (RAC-Standby-ASM).
- Acted as a consultant for software development tools, PL / SQL-forms-reports.
- Trained clients in Oracle database administration.
- Supported DBA clients (Falabella, Colombian Army, Thomas Express, Movistar).
- Visited clients on business sites, provided quotes configuration and created systems reports for clients and management.

SBD LTDA

October 2007 - August 2008

Position: Oracle Database Administrator

- Created users and privileges according with their responsibilities
- Configuring backup and restore procedures with RMAN scripts
- Tuned Oracle Sentences
- Developed scripts with PL / SQL and Shell scripting on Unix environments for DBA automated tasks
- Created and interpreting statspack reports
- Supported on call 24/7 DBA .

GEOSPATIAL

April 2007 - October 2007

Position: Development Leader Database

- Managed the Oracle development team on activities related with PL / SQL and Oracle Forms-Reports programming.
- Geodatabase Modeling, Use Case Specification
- Analyzed and design solutions according to the client requirements using RUP methodology
- Meeting clients face to face and on site to ascertain requirements.
- Producing and updating relevant documentation.

INFORMATICA SIGLO 21

November 2005 - March 2007 Position: Consulting Engineer

- Oracle10g Programming (Forms Builder, Reports Builder, PL / SQL)
- Development of New Buildings module and ranking contractors in Gas Natural ESP
- Application Maintenance NGV (Natural Gas Vehicle), IVM (Integrated Management of Sales), SAT
- Analyzed user requirements with UML methodology
- Design and Implementation of Business Applications using the Oracle Relational Database Management System (RDBMS).

SOFTMANAGEMENT

August 2003 - September 2005 Position: Senior Programmer

- Developed Complex database objects like Stored Procedures, Functions, Packages and Triggers using SQL and PL/SQL.
- Data analysis and generation of scripts for running reports
- Data analysis and generation of scripts for modification of information
- Change displays and programs Front-End, according to new requirements of the business.
- Programming Oracle (Forms 6i, PL / SQL and Reports), Procedures, Packages and Functions
- Involved in the support, maintenance, and development of the financial system
- Defining and generating screen formats and report designs using Oracle Forms and Oracle Reports
- Developed in accordance with policies regarding secure coding & standards
- Carrying out design, construction, review, and defect analysis activities.
- Developed using Oracle (Forms 6i, PL / SQL and Reports) in accordance with agreed design with consideration for usability, software quality and future maintenance

AVANZIT TECNOLOGÍA (new name Ezentis)

June 2000 - February 2002 Position: Oracle Developer

- Analysis and Design of security database modules
- Administration of databases in development and testing environment
- Project coordination SIGART for public sector telecommunication company

SYNERSIS S.A.S

September 1999 - June 2000 Position: Oracle Developer

- Analysis, design and programming of the human resources Information System
- Oracle Development using (Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5, SQLPLUS).
- Testing on QA environments for new software
- Defining and generating screen formats and report designs.
- Review and provide documentation for new developments.
- Develop software in accordance with agreed design with consideration for usability, software quality and future maintenance.

SOFTBOLIVAR - SEGUROS BOLIVAR

April 1998 - June 1999 Position: Oracle Developer

- Design and development of programs and reports for capitalization products
- Oracle Development using Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5, SQLPLUS

JOB REFERENCES

Please check my LinkedIn connections, some of them know me very well.

PERSONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

- Be able to adapt professionally and linguistically to support my family after moving from the country which I was born to the US 6 years ago.
- 5k runner in Orlando FL during two consecutive years
- Join the Catholic Christian community as an active member

PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

Four Oracle Certifications achieved

More than 20 notes published in Oracle Support Site related to Oracle Data Integrator issues I was able to solve, along with more than 300 data integration service requests solved globally.

"Could not load JDBC driver class [oracle.bi.jdbc.AnaJdbcDriver]" when Testing 2588136.1 Oracle BI Data Server Connection from ODI J2EE Agent

2514263.1 "The SQL Server login requires an SSL connection" Error Received when Testing Microsoft Azure SQL Database Service with ODI Agent

Attributes Missing in ODI Mappings after Using the OWB to ODI Migration Utility 2670516.1 Duplicate Database Hints Observed in ODI Code 2668348.1

java.lang.ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException Error Received when Using "LKM File 2601394.1

to Netezza (NZLOAD)" in ODI 12.2.1.3.190708

2273614.1 "ORA-01000: maximum open cursors exceeded" When Reverse Engineering ODI Models Including Datastore Subfolders

2655922.1 How To Call Multiple Commands in ODI for Oracle Data Server "On Connect/Disconnect" Events

- <u>2412849.1</u> Java Variable vPasswd Holding Wrong Cipher Data Value when Calling OdiSqlUnload "ORA-01017: invalid username/password"
- 2584874.1 ODI Studio Error Switching from Internal to Active Directory External Authentication
- <u>2571502.1</u> "ODI-17570: Your text is too long LONG TEXT" Error is Received When Smart Importing an ODI 12c Variable
- <u>2631697.1</u> How To Execute 'startloadplan.sh' From the Command Line without Providing the Supervisor Password
- 2374381.1 ODI Executions Fail With "Connection Closed" Message After Migration of the Repositories to Oracle RAC Database
- <u>2642094.1</u> Unknown RegionID Error: "ODI-14213: The Input Parameter Region Is Not Valid. It Is Null, Empty Or Incorrect" Encountered when Configuring Oracle Object Storage Dataserver in ODI 12.2.1.3 and Older
- 2686373.1 ERROR GENERATING ANSI QUERY ODI
- 2646498.1 ODI 12c Does Reverse Engineer XSD CLOB Datatype as VARCHAR2
- <u>2518862.1</u> "class java.sql.SQLDataException... numeric value out of range" Message is Received on ODI 12c Flows that Use XML Data Server
- 2649472.1 ODI Complex Driver Command 'CREATE XMLFILE' Results in "ORABPEL-11101 Translation Failure"
- ... A couple of notes more written but not published